Guide to the Thomas Moran Papers WAG.166
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Thomas Moran Papers
1975-1993
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Moran, Thomas
WAG.166
6 Linear Feet In 12 manuscript boxes and 2 oversize boxes
Thomas "Tom" Moran (1944-2012) was born and raised in New York City in an Irish-American working-class family. As shop steward of Local 1-2 of the Utility Workers Union of America (UWUA), and later as safety director, Moran fought for workers' rights to a safe and healthy workplace, clashing with Con Edison over radiation exposure, asbestos, PCBs (polychlorinated biphenyls), clean air, lead, and other instances of worker exposure to toxic substances without warning. Involved in several New York State Supreme Court cases as a plaintiff on behalf of UWUA, Moran represented workers in their struggle for workplace protections, legal enforcement, and provisions for protective equipment and preventive training. This collection, spanning Moran's work from 1975 to 1993, contains court records, correspondence with government bodies and advocacy groups, technical manuals, health and safety training materials, and citations given to Con Edison by regulatory bodies. These materials were collected by Moran in the course of his work as Safety Director for the UWUA and represent the issues, cases, training materials, and litigation related to the workplace safety of UWUA members working for Con Edison.
Biographical Note
Thomas "Tom" Moran was born and raised in New York City (1944-2012) in an Irish-American working-class family. Moran was a shop steward for Local 1-2 of the Utility Workers Union of America (UWUA) for much of his career in the labor movement. His father, uncle, and brother all worked for Con Edison, and his father helped lead the UWUA's union drive; Tom joined them in the ranks of the company in 1966. As shop steward of Local 1-2, and later as safety director, Moran fought for workers' rights to a safe and healthy workplace, clashing with Con Edison over radiation exposure, asbestos, PCBs (polychlorinated biphenyls), clean air, lead, and other instances of worker exposure to toxic substances without warning. Involved in several New York State Supreme Court cases as a plaintiff on behalf of UWUA, Moran represented workers in their struggle for workplace protections, legal enforcement, and provisions for protective equipment and preventive training. He developed close working relationships with politicians across New York State, lobbying connections for stronger labor protections and sanctions for environmental violations.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in four series: Seris I. Legal Documents; Series II. Correspondence; Series III. Worker Records; Series VI. Technical Materials. Files have been arranged in chronological order within each series.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials in Box 13 contain Protected Health Information (PHI) and are restricted until 50 years after the death of the individual in question.
Materials in Box 14 contain Personal Identifiable Information (PII) and are restricted until 2039.
The remaining materials in the collection are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Thomas Moran in 2000. The accession number associated with this gift is 2000.012.
Scope and Contents
The Thomas Moran Papers (1975-1993) document Moran's involvement in the labor movement in New York State, with specific regards to his years-long fight for workers' health and safety in utility professions. Beginning his career as a shop steward for Local 1-2 of the Utility Workers Unionof America (UWUA) and eventually rising to the role of Safety Director, the documents in this collection trace Moran's involvement in various legal campaigns against hazardous substances as a violation of workers' rights.
Documents in this collection address Moran's involvement in three New York State Supreme Court cases: Ostrowski v. Local 1-2 (1980), State of New York v. Consolidated Edison, Inc. (1982-1986), and Moran v. Vaccaro (1989). These cases deal with workers' wrongful exposure to asbestos without appropriate warning or protections, themes echoed in much of the collection in sum. The files regarding Ostrowski v. Local 1-2 and State of New York v. Consolidated Edison contain documents filed in court by the plaintiffs and defendants including motions, affidavits, judgments, and subpoenas. Files for Moran v. Vaccaro contain official court documents as well Moran's original whistleblower complaint and narratives written by doctors regarding injuries sustained by Con Ed employees. Supporting documentation submitted as evidence is overwhelmingly represented through citations issued to Con Edison by the Occupational Health and Safety Administration (OSHA), hazardous materials testing and monitoring reports compiled in response to complaints, and individual complaints filed by Moran himself.
Moran's working relationships other key stakeholders in the area of workplace safety is documented by correspondence with government bodies and advocacy groups, notably with Nancy Stearns of the New York Attorney General's Office. This correspondence highlights the existence and enforcement of New York's 1980 "Right to Know Law," which stated that employers had to alert employees to the possibility of exposure to hazardous materials in the workplace and provide appropriate information on protective gear and safety and also documents lobbying work done by Moran and others, including lawyers he also engaged to represent him in litigation, regarding other workplace safety laws and regulations. Letters from Moran to Janet Fox, director of Safety Services at Con Edison, also evidence of how Moran utilized Local 1-2's legal right to request information on sample analysis reports that could prove illegal substance exposure.
This collection also contains safety guides and technical manuals that document the workplace safety issues which concerned Local 1-2 workers throughout Moran's career.
Industrial safety -- New York (State) -- New York; Consolidated Edison Company of New York, inc.; New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health; Utility Workers Union of America. Local 1-2; Moran, Thomas
- Series I. Legal Documents, 1980-1993; 1 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes.
  Scope and Contents
  This series traces Thomas Moran's involvement in three New York State Supreme Court cases: Ostrowski v. Local 1-2 (1980), State of New York v. Consolidated Edison, Inc. (1982-1986) and Moran v. Vaccaro (1989). The documents in this series span a variety of phases of the cases' progress through the courts, including briefs from plaintiffs and defendants at multiple injunctions, correspondence between the New York State Attorney General's office and plaintiffs, and plaintiff affidavits. The initial letter to the plaintiffs in Moran v. Vaccaro and the forms accompanying the letter, including a questionnaire for plaintiffs surveying their medical history and details of exposure, is a significant document that frames much of the surrounding legal documentation although no completed questionnaires are included. A written statement from Richard Ostrowski, shop steward for Local 1-2, on his illegal removal from stewardship in retaliation for organizing around issues of radiation exposure, is also included.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Materials in Box 13 contain Protected Health Information (PHI) and are restricted until 50 years after the death of the individual in question.
  Materials in Box 14 contain Personal Identifiable Information (PII) and are restricted until 2039.
  - Ostrowski v. Utility Workers United of America, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
  - State of New York v. Consolidated Edison, Inc., 1982-1986 (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
  - Moran v. Vaccaro, 1987-1993 (Box 5, Box 13, Folder 2, Box 14)
- Series II. Correspondence, 1981-1992; 1.5 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes.
  This series contains Moran's correspondence with government bodies, advocacy groups, and lawyers concerning his work advocating for worker safety issues, specifically enforcement of New York state's 1980 "Right to Know Law," which states that employers have to alert employees to the possibility of exposure to hazardous materials in the workplace. The correspondence with lawyers and law firms in this series relates to Moran's advocacy work rather than any particular litigation. Of particular note are the initial letters between Moran and Janet Fox, director of Safety Services at Con Edison, in which Moran begins the process of requesting all asbestos variance reports to compile evidence for impending litigation.
  - National Labor Relations Board, 1981-1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Long Island College Hospital, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Alliance for Consumer Rights, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Right to Know" Toxic Substances in the Workplace A7103-D, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Central Labor Rehabilitation Council, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - New York City Department of Environmental Protection--Minor Projects and Air Monitoring, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Nancy Steans-Office of the Attorney General, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Proposed Laws, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Wilentz, Goldman & Spitzer, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Arthur Schwartz, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 1-4, Box 14, Folder 4)
  - New York State Department of Labor, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 5-7, Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Fred Sachs, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
  - Labor Management Committee, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Janet Fox, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
  - Federal Environmental Protection Agency, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Series III. Worker Records, 1983-1992; 1.5 Linear Feet In 2 manuscript boxes and two flat boxes.
  This series documents worker grievances and reports of health and safety violations at Con Edison worksites. Documents represent complaints filed with the Occupational Health and Safety Administration (OSHA), worker complaints surrounding specific Con Edison worksites such as Indian Point and Gramercy Park, and safety grievances filed by Local 1-2 members. These complaints are overwhelmingly represented through citations issued to Con Edison by OSHA, hazardous materials testing and monitoring reports compiled in response to complaints, and individual complaints filed by Thomas Moran himself. This series also contains reports from the Bureau of Labor Statistics that compile instances of workplace safety violations at Con Edison worksites from 1987, 1988, and 1989.
  - OSHA Complaints--ConEdison, 1983-1988 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Hudson Avenue Station, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Grievance reports, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Bureau of Labor Statstics--ConEdison, 1987-1989 (Box 11, Box 12)
  - Indian Point Drinking Water, 1988-1989 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Astoria Pipe Yard, 1988-1989 (Box 9, Folder 11-12, Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Gramercy Park, 1988-1989 (Box 10, Folder 1-2, Box 13, Folder 1, Box 14)
  - Federal EPA Complaints, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Tommy's day to day journal, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Member safety complaints, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 3, Box 14)
  - Worker testimony, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Federal OSHA Complaints, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 4-6)
- Series IV. Technical Materials, 1975-1991; 1.5 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes.
  Series IV consists of handbooks, safety manuals, safety guidelines, and other materials produced by health and safety organizations including the Environmental Protection Agency, Occupational Safety and Health Administration, City Department of Environmental Variance, National Lighting Bureau, and the New York Committee for Occupation Safety and Health. The contents cover a variety of hazardous substances and related issues that affected members of Local 1-2: radiation exposure, asbestos, PCBs (polychlorinated biphenyls), clean air, lead, pole-mounted transformers, fiberglass wool insulation, cumulative trauma disorders, electrical safety, cadmium, oxygen masks, electromagnetic fields, trench excavation, fire prevention, industrial hygiene, lighting, and others.
  - ConEd Safety Manual, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - ConEd--General Rules and Regulations, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Manuals, 1976-1987 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Asbestos Safety Manuals, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Fiberglass Wool, 1981-1987 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Iron, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Environmental Protection Agency Guidance for Controlling Asbestos Containing Materials in Buildings, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Medical Industrial Hygiene Safety, 1985-1990 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Hot Environments, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Polychlorinated Biphenyl (PCB), 1985-1990 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Polychlorinated Biphenyl (PCB) Cleanup, October 1989 (Box 6, Folder 11, Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - Asbestos Bulk Sample Analysys, 1988-1989 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - City of New York Department of Environmental Protection--Asbestos Variance, 1988-1990 (Box 7, Folder 4-7, Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - Penewet, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Electric and Magnetic Fields, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Cadmium, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Cortec VCI-309 Powder--Amine salts, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Safety eyeglasses problem, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Electrical safety, 1989-1990 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Solvents, 1989-1990 (Box 8, Folder 9-10)
  - Asbestos, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Hiring information, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Fire prevention, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Lighting, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - American Industrial Hygiene, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Safety and Health Conference, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Visual Terminal Display, undated (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Garlock Blue-Guard 300, undated (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Magnesium anodes, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Trench excavation, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)